Vandana Damodara . Jarvis Consulting

I am a qualified and experienced software engineer with three years of experience in the industry. I had completed my Bachelor of Technology degree in Electronics and Telecommunications. As a software developer, I believe that being able to work with/understanding lower levels of abstraction behind a program is a prerequisite to writing highly optimized code. I enjoy creative problem solving and getting exposure to multiple projects. I love working in a collaborative work environment. I am a Highly proficient, diligent, and excellent problem solver. As a Junior Data Engineer at Jarvis, I was able to participate in various challenging projects using an Agile/Scrum framework that allowed me to become proficient in technologies like Java, Git, SQL, Bash, Maven, and Docker. My experiences have taught me how to think outside the box when working, and I always strive to find the most optimized solution to the problem. I strive to stay current with relevant techniques and technologies

Skills

Proficient: Java, Linux/Bash, RDBMS/SQL, Agile/Scrum, Git **Competent:** Hive, Spark, Hadoop, C++, Python, Hadoop/HDFS

Familiar: MySQL, Scala, NoSQL, VBA, Unix

Jarvis Projects

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis_data_eng_VandanaDamodara

Cluster Monitor [GitHub]: Developed Cluster Monitoring agent which is used to monitor and collect data of various host machines connected through a network. The data that is collected includes hardware specifications, activity, and performances of machines in the cluster. Data is stored in PostgreSQL Database which is an RDBMS database provisioned with Docker Containers. Bash Scripts are used to initialize the process by creating psql container using Docker. Bash scripts are also used to monitor the host usage and host information data. This system uses crontab to collect real-time data every minute to generate statistics regarding resource utilization. The Monitoring agent sends the data to a database for storage and further analysis.

Core Java Apps [GitHub]:

- JDBC App: Constructed the JDBC application to perform CRUD operations using DAO and DTO design patterns on a PostgreSQL retail store's database
- Grep App: Programmed with Java 8 and leveraged its latest features including the stream API and lambda functions to develop an application similar to the Linux built-in grep feature. The program searches recursively through a root directory to map out all files and finds the lines that match the user-specified Java regular expression. Compilation was handled with the Maven tool, and the final product was packaged into a Docker container using Dockerfiles.
- The projects were designed, implemented, tested, and deployed with; Git, Docker, Bash Scripts, CentOS 7, Post-greSQL, Java 8 [Lambda/Steam Functions], Apache Maven, Mockito, DAO Design Pattern, Spring, JDBC API, Twitter Rest API, and Google Cloud Platform

Highlighted Projects

DataBase Design for Retail: Designed a Database for Retail Customer comprising of number of Entities by Entity Relationship diagram and Implementing the same by creating number of tables having primary keys and foreign keys to recognize the relationship Which had helped to ease the Querying of database .Used IBM DB2 for the same.

Professional Experiences

Software Developer, Jarvis (2021-present): Worked as a Data Engineer in a small Agile/Scrum environment to develop and implement solutions to various problems within the Jarvis team. The projects were implemented using Git/GitHub, Docker, Bash Scripts, CentOS 7, PostgreSQL, Python, Java SE 8, Apache Maven, JDBC API.Contributed to all the stages of software Development cycle through continous participation in scrum meetings and Agile best practices. Used Linux environment for all the projects.

System Engineer, Tata Consultancy services (2011-2014): Worked on various Projects comprising of Database management systems mostly working on MySQL,IBM Db2 using SQL language I had also able to Contribute to the complete lifecycle of software development (SDLC). Developed few Data ingestion projects to Big data . Worked on Hive queries

Education

Veer Surendra sai university of Technology (2007-2011), Bachelor of Technology, Electronics and Telecommunication - Scholarship

Miscellaneous

- AZ-900: Microsoft Azure Fundamentals
- IBM-Introduction to Data Engineering
- IBM-Introduction to Relational Databases (RDBMS)
- IBM-Databases and SQL for Data science with python